A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial records, New York Office, Series 22 FA365
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller gubernatorial records, New York Office, Series 22
1959-1965
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller)
FA365
28.2 Cubic Feet 60 legal boxes.
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson A. Rockefeller served as governor of New York from January 1, 1959, to December 18, 1973. He was the first person elected to four consecutive four-year terms as a state governor.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 15 22
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
This series is divided into 5 subseries:
Subseries 1 - Appointments Office, 1959-1965 Subseries 2 - Campaign for the 1964 Republican Nomination, March 1963-June 1964 Subseries 3 - Special Assistant to the Governor for Radio and Television, 1961-1965 Subseries 4 - George Hinman and Ilene Slater Files, 1959-1962 Subseries 5 - Rockefeller for President Citizens Information Center, 1958-1960
Biographical/Historical note
BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCHES
JERRY DANZIG
Mr. Danzig was born in New York City in 1913. He graduated from the Horace Mann School for Boys in New York and earned a B.A. from Dartmouth in 1934. He served in a variety of management and executive positions for broadcasting companies in New York City, including radio stations WOR and WINS, and television stations CBS and NBC. In 1961 he served as a television and radio consultant to the New York Republican City Committee. In 1962 he was made Special Assistant to the Governor for Radio and Television, a position he held until 1976. In this position Mr. Danzig's responsibilities included the production and distribution of radio and television commercials, or "spots," for Governor Rockefeller's gubernatorial and presidential campaigns. In 1973 Gov. Rockefeller appointed Mr. Danzig as a member of the New York State Commission on Cable TV, on which he served until 1981. Mr. Danzig was a partner in Chester Burger & Co., a management consulting firm, from 1976 until 1985 when he became a consultant to the National Executive Service Corps.
GEORGE L. HINMAN
Mr. Hinman was born in Binghamton, New York in 1905. He was a graduate of Princeton University, and held a bachelor of laws degree from Harvard University. He was also the recipient of many honorary doctoral degrees. He held directorships in many companies, including International Business Machines and New York Telephone. He was also a member of the executive committee of the Salvation Army New York State Advisory Conference. Mr. Hinman was at one time senior partner of the law firm of Hinman, Howard & Kattrell of Binghamton, a firm he was associated with since 1930. In his capacity as an attorney, he was also special counsel to the Rockefeller Family & Associates. He was a member of the Board of Regents of the University of the State of New York (1948-1950). After serving with the Governor, he was appointed to the Board of Trustees of the State University of New York in 1965. He also served as trustee of both Colgate University and Elmira College.
In addition to his position of executive assistant to the Governor (1958-1959), Mr. Hinman's state service consisted of being: Counsel for the New York State Temporary Commission on the Constitutional Convention and the Special Legislative Committee on the Revision and Simplification of the Constitution (1956-1958); a member of the New York State Attorney General's Committee on Ethical Standards in Government (1955-1959); and a member of the New York State Lt. Governor's Committee on Teachers' Salaries in 1951. Mr. Hinman was also Republican National Committeeman for New York State, as well as Delegate-at-large for the Republican National Conventions in both 1960 and 1964.
GRAHAM MOLITOR
Graham Molitor was born in Seattle in 1934. He earned a B.A. from the University of Washington in 1955 and an LL.B. from the American University in 1963. He was admitted to the bar in the District of Columbia in 1963. After working as a court bailiff in the District of Columbia and as a legislative counsel in the House of Representatives, Mr. Molitor was hired as Director of Candidate Research of the Rockefeller for President Committee in 1963. He was responsible for monitoring and analyzing statements made by other candidates for the Republican presidential nomination. He served until Gov. Rockefeller withdrew his candidacy in 1964, and then served in the same capacity again in Gov. Rockefeller's 1968 presidential campaign. From 1963 to 1977 he worked as a lobbyist for the food industry. In 1977 he established Public Policy Forecasting, Inc., and has written, lectured, consulted and participated in numerous public policy conferences all regarding future trends in food, technology, and related public policy issues.
ROSWELL "ROD" B. PERKINS
Mr. Perkins was born in Boston, Massachusetts, in 1926. He received an A.B. in 1945 and LL.B. in 1949, both from Harvard University. He was admitted to the bar in Massachusetts and New York in 1949. He spent his entire law career with the New York law firm of Debevoise, Plimpton, becoming a partner in 1957. He met Nelson Rockefeller when the two men worked for the Department of Health, Education and Welfare. Mr. Perkins served as Assistant Secretary (1954-1956) and Mr. Rockefeller served as Under Secretary (1953-1954). Mr. Perkins worked in Mr. Rockefeller's 1958 gubernatorial campaign, as well as some of his later campaigns. After the election of 1958 he assisted in establishing the new Rockefeller administration and served as Rockefeller's first Counsel to the Governor. As agreed to beforehand, Mr. Perkins resigned as Counsel on June 1, 1959, and returned to private practice.
MICHAEL N. SCELSI
Mr. Scelsi graduated from Louisiana State University with a degree in government in 1941. He served during World War II as a United States Marine stationed in the Pacific. From 1946 to 1948, he worked with the United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration and its successor agency, the International Refugee Organization. He was also very active in community and civic affairs in his native Broom County, New York. Prior to joining the Governor's staff, Mr. Scelsi worked in college administration, primarily at Harpur College of the State University of New York at Binghamton. He then went on to serve as Assistant Industrial Commissioner in the New York State Department of Labor. From 1959 to 1965, he served as executive director of the New York Republican State Committee. On February 1, 1967, after serving as Appointments Officer for two years, Governor Rockefeller appointed Mr. Scelsi to the New York State Civil Service Commission.
ILENE J. SLATER
Ms. Slater was graduated from Hunter High School in New York City, and received a B.A. from Mount Holyoke College in 1947. From 1947 to 1948, she also attended the Graduate Institute of International Relations, located at the University of Geneva, in Switzerland. She went on to work for the National Bureau of Economic Research (1948-1949), the English Speaking Union (1949-1950), the International Development Advisory Board (1951), the White House administrative staff (1953-1957), and the U.S. Commission for the Brussels Fair (1957-1958). In February of 1958, Ms. Slater became an assistant in the Offices of the Rockefeller Brothers Fund, and went on to join the Governor's personal staff in July 1958.
CARL SPAD
Mr. Spad was born in 1904 in Brooklyn, New York. He was educated in New York and Westchester County public schools. He maintained a manufacturer's representative office in New York City (1941-1947), served as a sales manager for a fuel oil concern (1947-1952), as president of the New York State Association of Young Republican Clubs and Youth Director for the Republican State Committee (1952-1954), as an executive assistant to the New York State Building Code Commission (1954-1956), and as assistant to New York State Republican Chairman, L. Judson Morehouse (1956-1959). Mr. Spad served as Gov. Rockefeller's Appointments Officer from 1959 until 1965, when he resigned to head the New York State Republican Committee. He was replaced by Michael N. Scelsi.
Sources: "The New York Red Book (An Illustrated Yearbook of Authentic Information Concerning New York State, Its Departments and Political Subdivisions, and the Officials Who Administer Its Affairs)," 68th edition (1959-1960), 76th edition (1967-1968).
"Who's Who in America," various editions.
Scope and Contents note
NOTE TO RESEARCHERS
This series contains the office files of Carl Spad, Michael Scelsi, Roswell B. Perkins, Graham T. Molitor, Jerry Danzig, George Hinman, Ilene Slater, and Alexander Halpern. They document the official activities of these individuals in the execution of their duties as members of Nelson A. Rockefeller's gubernatorial and/or political campaign staffs. The actions, decisions and exchanges of information or points of view documented here occurred in the course of proposing and implementing policies for the Rockefeller administration and/or political campaigns. However, unless a document is specifically addressed to or from Nelson A. Rockefeller, or is referred to in a document addressed to him, it should not be assumed that he saw the document or was aware of its existence or substance. Furthermore, researchers should bear in mind that staff files may contain documents addressed to Rockefeller that were never shown to him.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
Prior to his election as Governor of New York in November 1958, Nelson A. Rockefeller maintained an office at Rockefeller Center in Manhattan. To separate his work as Governor from his private activities, Governor Rockefeller established an office in Manhattan at 22 West 55th Street. This became known as the New York Office, to distinguish it from the Governor's office in the state capitol building in Albany. Governor Rockefeller was the first governor to maintain a permanent office in New York City. In general, Governor Rockefeller was in Albany only when the state legislature was in session or on special occasion. The management of his public duties was largely undertaken from the New York Office.
This series primarily documents Rockefeller's travel and public appearances during his first two terms as governor, portions of his 1962 gubernatorial reelection campaign, and portions of his campaigns for the Republican presidential nomination in 1960 and 1964.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Appointments Office (FA353)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Assembly and Senate Memos (FA354)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Joseph H. Boyd (FA355)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, James Cannon (FA356)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Affirmative Action (N. Lee Cook) (FA357)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Counsel's Office (FA358)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York State Committee to Reelect the President (FA359)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Jerry A. Danzig (FA360)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Executive Chamber (FA361)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, 55th Street (FA362)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Issue Books (FA363)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Arthur Massolo (FA364)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Hugh Morrow (FA242)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Civil Service Resolutions (Charles H. Palmer) (FA366)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Political Files (FA367)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Press Office (FA368)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Public Relations (FA369)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Departmental Reports (FA370)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, William J. Ronan (FA371)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Speeches (FA372)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Diane Van Wie (FA373)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Ann C. Whitman, Gubernatorial (FA374)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Gene Wyckoff (FA375)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Republican State Fund Raising Reports (FA376)
Vice-Presidents -- United States; United States; State governments -- United States; Public relations; Public policy; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Civil defense; Civil defense -- United States; Civil service; Civil service -- New York (State); Economics; Federal government -- United States; Government policy; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; International relations -- United States; International relations; International economic relations; Human rights; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; Affirmative action programs -- New York (State); Arms control; Arms control -- United States; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Political campaigns -- United States; Political science; New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Latin America; Legislation -- New York (State)
- Appointments Office, 1959-1965; 1; 9 Cubic Feet
  Arrangement note
  Subseries 1 is arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents note
  The Appointments Office maintained the Governor's schedule in this period. The Appointments Officer and his staff reviewed invitations to the Governor to speak or to attend events, and arranged the Governor's travel itineraries. They made arrangements for travel and accommodations and made sure that proper protocol was followed. This material also documents Rockefeller's extensive campaign trips in 1960, 1962, and 1964. The files date from November 1959 to December 1965. They contain correspondence, internal memoranda, the staff's handwritten notes regarding itineraries and scheduling problems, published itineraries for the benefit of the press, background information on the host organization for the benefit of Governor Rockefeller, transcripts of Governor Rockefeller's speeches and press conferences, programs from some events, lists of people to thank for assistance with some trips, and newspaper clippings. Some memoranda and letters contain Governor Rockefeller's handwritten comments. Correspondence regarding events Governor Rockefeller did not attend are filed as "Regrets."
  The first Appointments Officer was Carl Spad. He left in 1964 to head the New York State Republican Committee and was replaced by Michael Scelsi. The Appointments Secretaries were Margaret Fowler and Margaret Vilar.
  The cancellation of Governor Rockefeller's scheduled appearances in late November and early December of 1961 reflect his sudden trip to New Guinea to aid in the search for his son, Michael, who had disappeared there.
  - Providence, Rhode Island, November 20, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    1. Rhode Island Republican Committee 2. New England Society of Newspaper Editors
  - Washington, DC, January 27, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    1. Sheraton-Park Hotel
  - Regrets, January 1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    1. American Dental Association 2. Atlanta Insurance Company
  - Boston, Massachusetts, February 7, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    1. Visit with Henry Kissinger at his home 2. TV taping with Mrs. Eleanor (?) Roosevelt and Governor Martin at Brandeis University
  - New York City; Atlantic City, New Jersey, February 14, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    New York City 1. Viewed airing of "Citizens Union Searchlight" and "Direct Line" Atlantic City, New Jersey 1. American Association of School Administrators
  - Washington, DC, March 2, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    1. New Senate Office Building
  - Williamsport and Wellsboro, Pennsylvania, April 20, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    1. Williamsport - Lycoming County Republican Committee 2. Wellsboro - Schneebeli for Congress Committee
  - Albany, New York, April 21, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    1. Women's Council, Department of Commerce Luncheon
  - Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, April 22, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    1. World Affairs Council Luncheon 2. Tapping of "Eye on Philadelphia" at WCAU-TV
  - Chicago, Illinois, May 1, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    1. Lunch with University of Chicago President Dr. Lawrence A. Kimpton at his home 2. Visit to University of Chicago, new law buildings, and Rockefeller Memorial Chapel 3. Press Conference
  - North Dakota, June 3-5, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    June 3, Fargo 1. North Dakota State College 2. Appearances on WDAY-TV 3. Fargo Auditorium June 4 1. Breakfast at Mark Andrews' Farm 2. Valley City 3. Jamestown 4. Jamestown Crippled Children's School 5. Steel 6. Bismarck - Press Conference 7. Trails West Amphitheater 8. Appearance on KFYR-TV
  - Chicago, Illinois - Republican National Convention, July 18-28, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    1. Room assignments, travel plans, hotel bills, convention schedules
  - Brooklyn, New York, September 1, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    1. Opening of Kings County Campaign Headquarters
  - New York State, September 3, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    1. Meeting with Ambassador Henry Cabot Lodge (1960 Republican Vice-Presidential Candidate) at Grossinger's Lodge 2. Monticello - Rally at Concord Hotel 3. Ellenville - Neville Hotel 4. Middletown
  - New York, New York - Labor Day Events, September 5, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    1. Labor Day Parade 2. Tour of Jones Beach 3. Tour of Fort Tilden, Rockaway 4. Coney Island
  - New Jersey, September 9, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    1. Remarks at "Volunteers for Nixon" Headquarters 2. Press Conference with Senator Clifford Case 3. Patterson - Reception for Congressman Walter Kennedy 4. Dinner at "The Steak Pit" with Senator Case and guests 5. Paramus - Bergen Mall
  - Pennsylvania, September 10, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    1. Harrisburg - Scottish Rite Consistory Cathedral, press conference 2. State Committee Meeting 3. Quincy - Picnic
  - California, September 13-16, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    September 13 1. San Francisco - press conference 2. Fresno - Greeting by Young Republican Group 3. Fresno - Californian Hotel 4. Fresno - Roosevelt High School Auditorium - meeting with local leaders September 14 1. Sacramento - Eldorado Hotel Breakfast 2. Press Conference 3. Stanford University Business School, Bowman Alumni House 4. Berkeley - University of California 5. Richmond - Civic Auditorium - Press Conference 6. Sausalito - Alta Mira Hotel September 15 1. Los Angeles - Biltmore Hotel 2. Meeting and reception with local leaders and candidates 3. Compton Stadium - Democratic rally 4. Los Angeles City Hall - Mexican Independence Day celebration September 16 1. Long Beach - Breakfast, Junior Chamber of Commerce 2. Nixon's Home District
  - Taunton, Massachusetts, September 18, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    1. Testimonial Dinner for Joseph W. Martin
  - Delaware, September 19, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    1. Camden - Republican Dinner at Caesar Rodney High School
  - Ohio, September 22, 1960; Minnesota, September 23, 1960; Michigan, September 23, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Ohio 1. Toledo - Speech 2. Bowling Green State University 3. Fremont - Rally 4. WFRO-Radio 5. Norwalk - Rally, Huron County Fair 6. Lorain - Dinner, Clearview School 7. West Cleveland - Lakewood Civic Auditorium 8. Cleveland Wards - Cory Methodist Church Minnesota 1. Hibbing High School - Speech 2. Duluth - Kenwood Shopping Center 3. Duluth - Press Conference 4. Minneapolis - Reception at airport 5. Minneapolis - Rallies and appearances 6. Minneapolis - Dinner at Campus Club, University of Minnesota 7. Minneapolis - Northrup Auditorium Michigan 1. Battle Creek - Press Conference 2. Kalamazoo - Rally, Western Michigan University 3. Lansing 4. Pontiac 5. Berkeley 6. Oak Park 7. Inkster 8. Detroit - Statler Hotel 9. Detroit - Rally, Cobo Hall
  - New York, New York; Long Island, New York, September 28-29, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    1. Commodore Hotel - meeting with President Nixon 2. Motorcade with Nixon a. Long Island City Court House b. Rego Park c. Forest Hills Park d. May's Department Store e. Nassau County Court House f. Mid-Island Plaza, Hicksville 3. American-Scandinavian Foundation - reception for H.R.H. Crown Prince Harald of Norway at the Metropolitan Club 4. Waldorf-Astoria Hotel - Dinner for Prince Harald
  - New York, New York, October 4-5, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    1. Campaign Appearances with Vice President Nixon a. Commodore Hotel b. Fordham University c. Rockefeller Plaza d. Garment Center
  - Nassau County, New York, October 8, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    1. Whistle stop train trip through Seaford, Wantaugh, Bellmore, Freeport 2. Roosevelt Raceway, Luncheon and ceremonies for Long Island Industrial Exposition 3. Ribbon-cutting opening Long Island Fair 4. Dedication of Long Island Expressway extension (Guinea Woods Road) 5. Shopping Center appearances (2) 6. Uniondale - Nassau County Home for Senior Citizens 7. East Meadow - Reception for Senator Edward J, Speno 8. Garden City Hotel - Cerebral Palsy Association
  - New York State Campaign Appearances, October 10-22, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    October 10 1. Steuben County - Corning 2. Schuyler County - Watkins Glen 3. Yates County - Dundee 4. Yates County - Penn Yan 5. Ontario County - Geneva 6. Seneca County - Seneca Falls October 11 1. Chemung County - Elmira 2. Tioga County - Owego 3. Broome County - Endicott October 12 1. Parade - New York City 2. Monroe County - North Chili 3. Orleans County - Albion October 13 1. Genesee County - Batavia 2. Livingston County - Geneseo 3. Wyoming County - Arcade 4. Cattaraugus County - Olean October 14 1. Allegheny County - Wellesville 2. Allegheny County - Griffiths Air Force Base 3. Oneida County - Rome 4. Oneida County - Utica a. Munson-Proctor Institute b. Twin Pond Public Country Club October 15 1. Rensselaer County - Rensselaer 2. Columbia County - Hudson 3. Greene County - Catskill 4. Greene County - Coxsackie 5. Greene County - Schmollinger's Pleasant View Lounge October 17 1. Cayuga County - Auburn 2. Cortland County - Cortland 3. Tompkins County - Ithaca-Cornell 4. Tompkins County - Ithaca-Statler Inn October 20 1. Oswego County - Oswego 2. Madison County - Canastotoa 3. Madison County - Oneida 4. Chenango County - Norwich 5. Chenango County - New Berlin 6. Otsego County - Cooperstown October 21 1. Schoharie County - Cobleskill 2. Montgomery County - Amsterdam 3. Fulton County - Johnstown 4. Fulton County - Gloversville 5. Saratoga County - Saratoga Springs 6. Warren County - Glens Falls October 22 1. Dutchess County - Poughkeepsie 2. Dutchess County - Beacon - dedication of Newburgh-Beacon Bridge 3. Orange County - Newburgh 4. Ulster County - Kingston
  - New York State Campaign Appearances, October 23-29, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 26)